A Guide to the Sully Foundation Records, 1959-2009
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Sully Foundation Records, 1959-2009
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-42
2.5 linear feet
The Sully Foundation Records consist of 2.5 linear feet and span the years 1959-2009, and contains meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, financial reports, catalog records, invitations, newspaper clippings, brochures, microfilm, photographs, magazines, a galley proof, and a certificate.
Sully Foundation (1969-present)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
A small portion of this collection was donated at an unknown time. The Sully Foundation through Lee Hubbard donated the bulk of this collection in August 2010.
Historical and Biographical Information
In October 1969, Robert E. “Eddie” Wagstaff established the Sully Foundation Ltd. to promote and support the preservation and interpretation of the Sully Historic Site, also known as Sully Plantation. Henry Lee I purchased the plantation in 1725, and gave it to his son, Richard Bland Lee, in 1794. Several families lived on the plantation until the Fairfax County Park Authority acquired the site in 1959, saving it from demolition during the construction of Dulles International Airport.
Wagstaff, who was largely instrumental in saving Sully from destruction, formed the Sully Foundation to promote the site’s educational value and to maintain, further develop, and restore the house. The Foundation sought to use Sully for educational purposes by providing tours and encouraging visitors. The organization also sought to restore and furnish the plantation and its grounds through the solicitation of financial gifts and donations of artifacts. The Foundation consisted of a directorate of six to fifteen persons of which Wagstaff named the original group. Wagstaff died only a few months after he donated his life’s savings to create the Sully Foundation in August 1970.
In 1971, the Fairfax County Board of Supervisors expressed a desire to publish a manuscript on the history of Sully Plantation. The Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning appointed Robert S. Gamble to prepare a study which resulted in the 1974 publication of the book “Sully: The Biography of a House”. The Sully Foundation supported and underwrote the book’s publication and later received publication rights for it. Gamble’s book is now widely regarded as the definitive study on Sully Plantation.
In 1996, the Fairfax County Park Authority erected a plaque in front of Sully in commemoration of the Sully Foundation’s many years of service towards preserving the house.
Scope and Content
The Sully Foundation Records consist of 2.5 linear feet and span the years 1959-2009, and contains meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, financial reports, catalog records, invitations, newspaper clippings, brochures, microfilm, photographs, magazines, a galley proof, and a certificate. Subjects covered are the Sully Foundation’s efforts in preserving and promoting Sully Plantation.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1959-2009, Boxes 1-2
This series contains meeting minutes, correspondence, reports, articles of incorporation papers, magazines, periodicals, a book, invitations, newspaper clippings, and a certificate. Meeting minutes, correspondence, and staff reports are interfiled together chronologically as was maintained by the Sully Foundation. Of particular note is a letter from 1975 signed by First Lady Betty Ford in which she declined an invitation to Sully’s restoration reception.
Series 2: Financial Records, 1970-2008, Boxes 2-3
This series contains financial statements, reports, and account books for the Sully Foundation.
Series 3: Photographs, 1967-1974, Box 3
The photographs in this series depict various scenes at Sully including Robert Gamble’s 1974 book signing for “Sully: The Biography of a House” which was attended by Mary Haight, Alex Haight, and Ben Peck; the 1967 Garden Week Candlelight tour at Sully; various women in period dress at Sully; and a street map of the Falls Church, VA area. Also included is an undated print of Sully depicted as it looked circa 1800 by Joseph Pisani.
Series 4: Catalog Records, 1962-1980, Box 4
Throughout its existence, the Sully Foundation acquired books, periodicals, and artifacts of which they maintained catalog records for. There are two duplicate sets of catalog records included in this series; one set is in a folder and another in a small box.
Series 5: “Sully: The Biography of a House”, 1974-1994, Boxes 4-5
This series contains the cover and galley proof for “Sully: The Biography of a House” by Robert S. Gamble, as well as Gamble’s author’s introduction to the 1994 edition. Also included is a microfilm reel containing the Haight-Barlow Papers which consists of genealogical papers, correspondence, miscellaneous deeds, contracts, receipts, business papers, and an account book dating from 1816-1889 from the Haight-Barlow family of Sully. Robert Gamble received permission to microfilm these papers from their owners, Mr. and Mrs. Vernon W. Barlow, Sr. of Humboldt, Kansas. The current status and location of these papers is unknown.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Robert S. Gamble Manuscript Papers on “Sully the Biography of a House”, MSS 08-06, Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
None
Index Terms
Gamble, Robert S.; Historic buildings -- Virginia-- Fairfax County; Leigh, Lewis, Jr.; Plantations -- Virginia -- Fairfax County; Sully Foundation, Inc.; Sully Plantation (Fairfax County, Va.); Wagstaff, Robert Edward "Eddie"
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Records, 1959-2009
  - Articles of Incorporation and Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation Amendments, Tax Exemption Status, and Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 1980-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes, Correspondence, and Reports, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Legislation relating to Second Washington Airport" (History of the Sully Planation on pages 7-21), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Report on Restoration of Sully Plantation, Chantilly, Virginia for Fairfax County Park Authority, Garland A. Wood & Associates, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Magazine, "Echoes of History" Vol. 1, No. 3 (article about Little Sully), 1971 March (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Magazine, "Virginia Cardinal" ("Christmas at Sully" by Claire S. Muller, pg. 25), 1972 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Book, "A History of the Fairfax County Park Authority", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sully Dwelling House Downspouts Selected Documentation, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - A Furnishings Plan for the South Lane Slave Quarters a Representative Exhibit at Sully Historic Site by Jeanne Niccolls, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Highlights of the Sully Restoration, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Invitation, Reception honoring Robert S. Gamble, author of "Sully: The Biography of a House", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Invitation, Freedom Hill Chapter, NSDAR installation of Historic Marker at Sully, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Invitation, 200th anniversary of Sully Plantation, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Brochures, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings [photocopies], Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Certificate of Resolution, Sully Foundation donation to Fairfax County Park Authority for Sully fire and security system [includes photos of Mayo Stuntz accepting plaque], 1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Series 2: Financial Records, 1970-2008
  - Account book, 1988-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Account book, 1996-2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Financial Report, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Financial Report, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Financial Reports, 1974-1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Financial Reports, 1980-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Financial Reports, 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Financial Reports, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Financial Reports, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Financial Reports, 2000-2005 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Financial Reports, 2006-2008 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series 3: Photographs, 1967-1974
  - Garden Week Candlelight Tour, Debbie Jackson, Lorraine Cross, unidentified woman, 1967 April 23 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Mary Haight, Alex Haight, Ben Peck at Sully Plantation book signing, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Robert S. Gamble and others at Sully Plantation book signing, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Betty Merriam posing in front of Sully fireplace [3 photos], Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Betty Merriam and Lynn Woodard in period dress [2 photos], Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Jean Stallings in period dress on Sully's front porch [2 photos], Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Street map of Falls Church area, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Print, Illustration of Sully Plantation circa 1800 by Joseph Pisani, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Series 4: Catalog Records, 1962-1980
  - Catalog Record Cards, 1962-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Sully: The Biography of A House, 1974-1994
  - Microfilm, Haight-Barlow Papers, 1816-1889, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Cover, "Sully: The Biography of a House", Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Author's Introduction, "Sully: The Biography of a House", 1994 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Galley proof, "Sully: The Biography of a House", Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)